## FRANCISCO TOLOSA



# Bachelor of Business // Data Analytics Currently studying Management and Leadership - SAIT

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Professional with experience in project planning and administrative support across various industries. Tasks have included managing documentation, monitoring project timelines, and assisting teams in meeting operational goals. Familiar with maintaining data accuracy, preparing reports, and coordinating multiple tasks. Background includes working in dynamic environments and supporting communication and collaboration among team members.

### AREAS OF EXPERTISE

### **Technical Skills:**

- Programming with Python | Programming with R | Data Analytics using Python | Data Analytics using Excel | Data Analytics using R | Machine Learning using Python | Machine Learning using R | Neural Networks and Deep Learning using Python | Neural networks and Deep Learning using R | Natural Language Processing using Python | Expert Systems using Python | Database Design and Development using MySQL | Business intelligence and Reporting using Excel, Power BI and Tableau | Design using Canva
- Software: Python, R, Excel, Tableau, Power BI, Visual Studio Code, Canva

## **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

## Data Analyst, PHUI. City of Wetaskiwin (Volunteer), Calgary, Alberta

Sept 2024 – Present

- Designed administrative procedures for data management at Peace Hills Utilities Inc.
- Managed data to improve decision-making processes.
- Optimized processes to enhance efficiency in water resource management.
- Designed a comprehensive handbook outlining the company's history, board composition, financial results, policies, and bylaws, serving as a key resource for both internal and external stakeholders.

## Operation Manager, Metrogas - Naturgy/ Chile

May 2017- Oct 2023

- Planned and executed complex natural gas pipeline projects, including the annual construction and installation of 50 km pipelines for 300 customers, ensuring on-time delivery, high-quality work, and adherence to sustainability standards.
- Coordinated the planning and operation of network installations, conversions for businesses and homes, increasing efficiency across conversion, marketing, construction, technical service, and emergency response departments.
- Contributed to the development and execution of a successful business plan, achieving a 95% completion rate of planned objectives.
- Managed and resolved customer requests and complaints within established timeframes, maintaining high service quality.

- Ensured successful execution of contracts with partnership companies, including project assignments and timely payment processing.
- Contributed to the preparation of annual budgets, variance monitoring and management reports, investment proposals, quarterly forecasts, and consumption analyses for private and commercial markets

## Chief Operating Officer, Workers' Health Hospital (ACHS)/ Chile

Apr 2016 - Jan 2017

- Ensured efficient patient care: Streamlined processes from admission to discharge, improving patient experience and service quality.
- Maximized patient outcomes: Determined productive capacity and implemented strategies to enhance patient recovery and return to work.
- I motivated and led high-performance teams of up to 35 people, creating a positive and productive work environment that resulted in the achievement of key performance indicators (KPIs) and organizational goals.

## Project Manager, Chilean Association of Security (ACHS)/ Chile

Jun 2014 - Agus 2015

- I streamlined internal processes and developed valuable tools to enhance preventive care services
  for the organization's collaborators, including the control board for compliance with objectives and
  productivity by department.
- Implemented SAP front office, promoting user adoption through training initiatives.

#### **RECOGNITIONS AND AWARDS**

- Recognition of "Chief performance", METROGAS / 2020 and 2021
- Recognition of "Urgency sense", ACHS / 2016
- Recognition of Excellence. Compensation Fund "Los Andes" / 2013

#### **VOLUNTARING**

**Calgary Food Bank:** I currently volunteer at the Food Bank, specifically in the distribution area. My role involves sorting and packaging food for delivery to families in need. I appreciate the opportunity to contribute to the community and continue learning while supporting this important cause.

**Volunteer, Calgary Folk Fest 2024:** Worked behind the scenes assisting in the coordination and safeguarding of musical instruments. Ensured smooth operations and contributed to the overall success of the event.

#### **EDUCATION**

Data analytics and Management and Leadership, SAIT Calgary – Canada, 2024

**Diploma in Organizational Leadership Skills, Pontifical Catholic University of Chile** Santiago – Chile, 2022

Select English Advanced, St. Andrew College Cambridge - England, Aug 2015 - Feb 2016

Bachelor of Business Administration, University of Talca. Chile, 2005 - 2010